Guide to the Detering Family & Business Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Detering Family & Business Papers
1871-1989
05/2014-009
Detering family
9.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains deeds, abstracts of title, legal files, real estate sales records, and many other materials related to businesses and properties held by various members of the Detering family from 1871-1989.
Family History:
The Detering family has lived and worked in the Houston area for over a century, owning numerous Houston properties and several long-standing businesses. Herman Eberhard Detering (1862-1927) moved from Germany to Houston, Texas in 1881. Upon moving to Houston, his first job was working for Henke’s Grocery. Soon after, Detering purchased a lot at 3028 Washington Avenue, where he opened the Detering General Store. He married Helena “Lina” Stuer in 1891, and they made their home above the store. The five Detering children, Alma, Elsa Anna, Herman Eberhard, Carl August, and Lenora Lina, were all born at home on Washington Avenue. In 1895, Mr. Detering bought another business, the Houston Broom Factory, and located it behind the grocery store, on Center Street. The grocery store was closed in approximately 1913, after the family moved to McGowen Street. Herman Eberhard Detering also became a real estate entrepreneur early on, buying and selling land all over the Houston area. According to family lore, Eberhard believed Houston waterways would be used for transportation but did not know which bayous would be important, so he bought on all of them. He had several real estate partnerships, including Bottler & Detering and Kalb & Detering.
The Detering children continued in the family businesses and real estate ventures. In 1926, Carl Detering opened The Detering Company, a provider of building materials and supplies, in the same location as their father’s grocery store. He was joined shortly thereafter by his brother, Herman. Alma Detering kept an office at the Detering Company as well, and ran the Houston Broom Factory from there until its closure in the 1940s. Alma also oversaw the accounting for the family’s other businesses and properties during this time. The Woodridge Company (a partnership between Herman and Carl) and Carl Detering Developer (a business in which Alma and Herman were also heavily involved) are two examples of businesses created by the Detering children to manage real estate development. Other companies associated with the Detering family included the Detering Concrete Tile Company, Turning Basin Development Company, the Detering Company of Beaumont, Inc., and the Detering Galleries.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Detering family
Genre/Form of Material:
Estate Records; Financial records; Legal documents; Property records
Geographic Name:
Houston (Tex.) -- History
Topical Term:
Commercial real estate -- Texas -- Houston; Real property -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains deeds, abstracts of title, legal files, real estate sales records, and many other materials related to businesses and properties held by various members of the Detering family from 1871-1989. The collection has been divided into five series: Properties, Legal Files, Trust and Estate Papers, Business Papers, and Financial Papers. Folders within each series (or subseries) are arranged chronologically.
Detailed List of Contents
- Properties
  - Deeds and Abstracts
    - Abstracts and Deeds - Various, 1871-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abstracts and Deeds - Various, 1891-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Abstracts - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 14, 1895-1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Deeds and Original Papers - E.C. Crawford Addition, 1909-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Abstracts to Ross Property and 30 acres Jacob Thomas survey, 1909-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Abstracts to Ross Property and 30 acres Jacob Thomas survey, 1909-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Abstracts covering Woodridge Subdivision Section 1 and Detering Addition, 1910, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Abstracts - Luke Moore League, 40 acres of Lot 11, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Abstracts to Suburban Addition, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Abstracts - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 14, 1922-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Abstracts - Land in John R. Harris and the H.B. Prentiss Survey, 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Detering Abstract covering Smith and Gibbons Addition, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Abstracts - Smith and Gibbons Addition, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Abstract of Title - Land in Busch subdivision of Eli Noland Survey, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Abstract of Title - Land in Busch subdivision of Eli Noland Survey, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Detering Abstract covering Blocks 1-5 Woodridge Section 1, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Abstract and Original Papers - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 5, Lots 2, 3, and 8, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Deeds, Abstracts, Surveys - Moers Tract, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Abstract and Original Papers - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 5, Lots 4-7, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Saddlebrook Subdivision Deed and Restrictions, 1952, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Abstract and Original Papers - Park Place Lot, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Deed from Ben G. McGuire to Carl Detering - Half block on Fannin Street, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sales, Leases, and Purchases
    - Various land sales by Lina Detering, 1936-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Purchase of land in John R. Harris and the H.B. Prentiss Survey from Katherine H. Moers, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Lease to W&S Realty Corporation - Brunner Addition, Block 46, 1945-1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lina Detering - Resale of Cedar Lane tract to Bishop Hines, for church, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lease of land to International Harverster Company, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Purchase from George - Daniel, Crawford Addition land, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Sale to Jones Apothecary - Suburban Addition, Block 7, Lots 1, 2, 25, and 26, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Sale to Bethany Christian Church - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 4, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Sale to Texas Highway Department - Katy Highway, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sale to Bruce Bristol - Suburban Addition, Blocks 6 (partial) and 7, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sale to Bethany Christian Church - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 4, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Lease to Telephone Road Lions Club - Woodridge and Winkler, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sale of land to Jagger Associates, Inc. (folded map/plans), 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sale to Inrope Corporation - Suburban Addition lots, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Sale to City of Houston - Elgin-Beulah-Lockwood Grade Separation, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Proposed sale to Housing America Corporation and Inwood Construction Company - E.C. Crawford Addition, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Sale to Dietrich F. Gothe - Camp Logan Cement Works, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Texaco, Inc. Station Site Lease - Katy Road, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Lease to United Aircraft Corporation - Gulf Freeway, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Purchase of land - LaPorte Interchange, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Bulletin Board Sign Leases - LaPorte Interchange, 1963, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Lease to Humble Oil and Refining Company - Land in Alexander Ewing survey, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lease of land to Blaz'r Steaks, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Memorial Drive and Detering St (2 proposed sales, both called off), 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Control Data Corporation Lease - Buildings 2 and 4, 1963-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Control Data Corporation Lease - Buildings 2 and 4, 1963-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Detering Family lease to Brazer's Inc. - Triangle tip Gulf Freeway, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lease to Walter Tropst - Woodridge Drive and Gulf Freeway, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Lease to Woodridge Corporation (same as Marvin Leggett) - West Side Woodridge Drive, South Freeway, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lease to M& P Building Corporation - Woodridge Drive and Gulf Freeway, 1964-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Proposed sale of 10 acres north of Houston to Jamaica Corporation, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Herman E. Detering sale of Wirt Road area to city, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Detering lease to Chrysler Motors Corporation - Woodridge and Gulf Freeway, 1965-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Detering Family sale to Welcome E. Wilson - H. Busch survey, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Amendment to lease to Gateway Employment Service - Office City Buildings, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sale of land to Lincoln Properties, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Resale of Lot 1286, Block 66, Hawthorne Place by H.E.D. Trustee, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Sale to Walter P. Moore - Land in E.C. Crawford Addition, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Carl A Detering lease to S.K. Vincent - Putt Putt Golf Course, tract in Alexander Ewing survey, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Detering Family lease to Liberty Sign Company - Katy Road, November 17, 1967-November 17, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Lease to B.F. Goodrich Company - Gulf Freeway and Winkler Drive, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Sale of land to La Quinta Motor Inns, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Sale to Walter P Moore - E.C. Crawford Addition, Block 19, Lots 19, 20, and 21 (partial), 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Proposed lease to RSC Management Company (no deal made), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Saddlebrook Subdivision lot sold to Thomas E. Greacen and wife, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Proposed sale to Unit, Inc. (no deal resulted), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Detering lease to Humble Oil and Refining Company - Corner Gulf Freeway and Woodridge, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Detering lease to Dot Systems Inc. - Gulf Freeway thru to Winkler, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Lease to Robee's Franchise of Houston - Corner of Woodridge and Winkler, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Sale to James C. Smith - Brashear Addition, Block 5, Lot 6, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Lease to John W. Moore, III - Land in Luke Moore survey, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Detering Lease to Virgil Boll (Pizza Hut), 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Lease to Shell Oil Company - Commerce Central, Block 2, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Sale to State Highway Commission, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Detering lease to Mobil Oil Corporation (service station) - Gulf Freeway and Winker Drive, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Purchase of land from Philip Getz - Washington Avenue and Studemont Street, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Purchase of land from City of Houston - Washington Avenue and Studemont Street, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Sale of land to Texas Highway Department, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Washington Avenue property - Attempted purchase from Leonard Golasinki, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Detering Family sale to James P. Lee, Trustee - Several lots, Suburban Addition Block 1, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Washington Avenue Property - Purchase from Helen Delmont, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Herman Detering sale to Billie Frazier (widow of Parkhurst Frazier) - Freeway Manor, Block 3, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Oil, Gas and Mineral lease - Five Detering children to Austral Oil Company, Inc., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Detering lease to Humble Oil and Refining Company (service station) - Woodridge and Office City Drive, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Willow Creek Apartments - Harold Farb deal, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
    - Sale to Luther High School - Old maps of commerce central and other matter, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sale of land to Texas Highway Department, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Detering Family sale to Lutheran High School Association - Tract in John R. Harris survey, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Subdivions and Properties
    - Lucky Seven Addition - J.H. Weisenberger, 1900-1944 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Detering Land Book (surrogate copy), 1915 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Travis Street Property - Alma and Lenora Detering, 1934-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Woodridge Subdivision, 1939-1963 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Woodridge Section IV, 1940-1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - E.C. Crawford Addition, 1940-1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Woodridge Section IV Restrictions, 1941-1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Saddlebrook Subdivision records, approximately 1941-1985 (Box 5, Folder 11-17)
    - C.G. Fitze Homestead Addition - Block 12, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ordinance vacating and abandoning a portion of Woodridge Drive Subdivision, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ship Channel Property, 1948-1963 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Rent Houses - Paul J. Wooley, et al, 1949-1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sadddlebrook Subdivision Architectural Committee Amended Restrictions, etc., 1952, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Dallas at Sam Houston Park, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Suburban Addition - Condemnation, 1954-1970 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
    - Leverkuhn Addtion - Block 8, 1956-1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Brays Bayou Rectification - Spoil Disposal Contract with Harris County Flood Control District, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous - Woodridge and Winkler corners, 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Saddlebrook Subdivision - Lot 15, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - E.C. Crawford Addition Exchanges - Blocks 14 and 16, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Office City, Commerce Central - General, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Carl and Herman - Legal Exchange Papers, Woodridge and Winkler, 1950s, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Suburban Addition - South of Freeway, 1961-1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Office City records, 1962-1969 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Cherry House restoration - Harris County Heritage Society, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Crawford Survey - Hi Rise Apartments, Irving Klein, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - E.C. Crawfod Addition - Blocks 5 and 6, 1964-1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Old Broom Factory Property - Wagner Street, 1964-1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Sackett Street Property - Rear encroachment, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 3100 West Alabama - Construction Specifications, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Crawford Addition and Office City Buildings, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Leverkuhn Property, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Memorial Drive and Aloe Street, 1967-1972 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - E.C. Crawford Addition - Walter P, Moore, 1967-1988 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Saddlewood Subdivision - Lot 8, restrictions (nothing done), 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Carl and Herman - Exchange Deeds, E.C. Crawford Addition, 1960s, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - E.C. Crawford Addition - Several lots, 1960s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Land - Gulf Freeway and S. Loop East, 1972-1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Office City, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Old Detering Maps and Plans, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Legal Files
  - Mrs. Lina Detering vs. H. & T. C. R.R. Co. and City of Houston, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Mrs. Lina Detering Legal File, 1935-1948 (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
  - The Detering Company vs. E. Calvert Smith, 1937-1940 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Carl A. Detering vs. Alexander Ewing et al, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Carl A. Detering General Legal File, 1939-1949 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Herman Detering, Jr. General Legal Papers, 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - County of Harris vs. Herman Detering, 1941-1943 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - County of Harris vs. Carl A. Detering, 1941-1943 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Pacific Trading Co., Inc., vs. Standard Rice Company, Inc., et al, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - City of Houston vs. Herman E. Detering, et al, 1950-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - A.H. Krueger vs. Helen Johnson Chatman, et al - Transcript of Testimony, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - City of Houston vs. Katherine Moers - Paving assessment on Berkeley Street, 1955-1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Detering legal files, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Harris County Flood Control District - Core boring license, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Carl A. Detering General Legal File, 1964-1972 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Lina Detering Estate vs. George Brooks (colored) - Tenant 3416 Washington Avenue, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - LaPorte Freeway Construction Easement, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - City of Houston sanitary sewer easement for Winkler and Gulf Freeway, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Carle Detering vs. Federal Sign Company, 1967-1971 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Houston Lighting and Power easement to serve Office Building 4, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Alma Detering Legal Files, 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Ram-Hart Systems, Inc. - Bankruptcy of Robee's Franchise of Houston, 1969-1972 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Trust and Estate Papers
  - Herman and Carl Detering - Trustees for children, 1923-1925 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Detering Estate - General, 1926-1930 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - H.E. Detering Estate, 1927-1928 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - H.E. Detering Estate - Busch Subdivision partition, 1930s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Detering Estate - General, 1931-1934 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Lina Detering Estate Files, 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Lina Detering Estate, 1950-1965 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Lina Detering - Miscellaneous Estate Files, 1950-1989 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Trusts Created by Lina Detering, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Lina Detering Estate Files, 1953-1958 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Trust #3 - Carl and Herman for children of each, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Trust Files - Alma Detering, 1955-1969 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Estate of Mrs. Lina Detering, 1958-1973 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - 1954 Trusts - General Matters, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Detering Trusts - Exchange of properties, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Opinion on 1954 Trust as to Allocation of Income and Expenses, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Herman E. Detering - Copies of gift deeds to son and daughter, Herman Detering, III and Mrs. Deborah Inez Pannill, approximately 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Detering Heirs - Vendor's Lien to release Angel and Porfiria Rodriguez, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Herman E. Detering - 1976 Trusts for Children and Grandchildren, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Detering Estate, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Lina Detering Estate Files, 1928-1981 (Ovs box 10, Folder 1)
- Business Papers
  - The Detering Company - General, 1926-1935 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Detering Company - General, 1936-1954 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Phylcar Corporation - General, 1949-1965 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Phylcar Utilities Inc., 1950-1961 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - McGowen-Austin Corporation, 1952-1960 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Standard Rice Company - Final liquidation, 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Financial Papers
  - Bank Records - Alma Detering, 1957-1967 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Tax Letters and Other Information, 1959-1971 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - All Detering Bills, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Tax Records, 1970-1976 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Freeway Warehouse Tax Return, 1971-1975 (Box 9, Folder 16)